A Finding Aid to the Charles Keck Papers, circa 1905-circa 1954, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Charles Keck papers
circa 1905-circa 1954
Archives of American Art
Keck, Charles, 1875-1951
AAA.keckchar
Archival Resource Key
8.6 Linear feet
The papers of New York City sculptor Charles Keck (1875-1951) measure 8.6 linear feet and date from circa 1905-circa 1954. The papers provide scattered documentation of Keck's life through thirteen letters, two speeches, lists of artwork with price and sales information, printed material, and photographic material, including photos of Keck and his studio, and a collection of 1003 glass plate negatives, primarily of Keck's artwork, which document the wide range of work he produced throughout his prolific career.
Biographical / Historical
New York City sculptor Charles Keck (1875-1951) was known for his statuary and relief sculpture, including military and presidential statues, busts, and memorials, medal relief sculpture, and memorial tablets.
Keck was born in New York City, and began his art training at the National Academy of Design and the Art Students League of New York. He also worked in the studio of Augustus Saint-Gaudens from 1893-1898. In 1899 he won the Prix de Rome and studied sculpture at the American Academy in Rome from 1901-1904. On returning to the United States in 1905, he opened a studio in New York City, from which he worked for the remainder of his life.
Keck's most famous works include a figure of Booker T. Washington at Tuskegee, Alabama (1922), a seated figure of Abraham Lincoln at Wabash, Indiana (1926), a statue of World War II chaplain, Father Francis D. Duffy in Times Square, New York (1937), and equestrian statues to Andrew Jackson in Kansas City (1934) and Independence (1949), Missouri. His relief work included designs of state medals, seals, and coins, memorial tablets such as his USS "Maine" tablet, and friezes for the Nelson Atkins Museum in Kansas City, Missouri, and the Bronx Building in New York.
Keck received many awards during his career, including the Annual Gold medal for Sculpture of the Architectural League of New York (1926), and was a member of professional art organizations including the National Academy of Design, the National Sculpture Society, the American Federation of Arts, and others.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as two series.
Series 1: Personal Papers, 1920-circa 1954 (0.3 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Photographic Material, circa 1905-circa 1948 (8.3 linear feet; Boxes 1-22)
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Existence and Location of Copies
The bulk of the collection was digitized in 2019 and is available on the Archives of American Art's website. Materials which have not been digitized include blank pages, the full text of a publication, blank versos of photographs, and duplicates including copy prints of glass plate negatives.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was loaned for microfilming, and the bulk of it was later donated, between 1962-1972 by Anne C. Keck, widow of Charles Keck.
Scope and Contents
The papers of New York City sculptor Charles Keck (1875-1951) measure 8.6 linear feet and date from circa 1905-circa 1954. The papers provide scattered documentation of Keck's life through thirteen letters, two speeches, lists of artwork with price and sales information, printed material, and photographic material, including photos of Keck and his studio, and a collection of 1003 glass plate negatives, primarily of Keck's artwork, which document the wide range of work he produced throughout his prolific career.
Keck's thirteen letters include two from Alexander Stirling Calder and one from Homer Saint-Gaudens. His lists of artwork include details of contracts, payments, and prices.
Photographs include Keck, his wife, Anne Keck, two photos from a circa 1920 Beaux Arts ball, photographs of Keck at work in his studio, including one taken at the American Academy in Rome, three group photographs of Keck, Adolph Weinman, Milton Horn, and others, and photos taken at the unveiling of Keck's monument in Raleigh, North Carolina, that include President Harry S. Truman and Margaret Truman.
Separated Materials
The Archives of American Art also holds microfilm of material lent for microfilming (reel D105) including scrapbooks containing clippings, speeches, photographs, and some correspondence. Items were returned to the donor after microfilming and are not further described in the container listing of this finding aid.
Sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York; Weinman, Adolph A. (Adolph Alexander), 1870-1952; Calder, Alexander Stirling, 1870-1945; Saint-Gaudens, Augustus, 1848-1907
- Personal Papers, 1920-circa 1954; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes three biographical statements written by others about Keck, including an entry for the National Cyclopedia of American Biography; a diploma given to Keck in recognition of distinguished service in the field of Lincolniana from Lincoln Memorial University; thirteen letters to Keck, including two from Alexander Stirling Calder and one from Homer Saint-Gaudens; typescripts of two speeches given by Keck, to the Allied Artists, and as president of the National Sculpture Society; and printed material including news clippings from 1933 and 1948, statements released about the addition to the General Post Office building in New York City, for which Keck was selected to create a relief sculpture, and a collection of addresses and papers printed in connection with the unveiling of Keck's monument to Andrew Jackson, James K. Polk, and Andrew Johnson in Raleigh, North Carolina in 1948. Lists of artwork include a bound volume listing works alphabetically and giving drawer locations for some of the works; a loose leaf binder of records entitled "Work done" providing overviews of projects including dates of contracts, creation, payments, and some descriptive information about Keck's ideas for the works and his artistic process; and four other loose leaf lists, one of which includes prices.
  Existence and Location of Copies
  This series has been digitized in entirety with the exception of the full text of the publication "Presidents North Carolina Gave the Nation" and a binder originally housing lists of artwork.
  - Biographical Statements, circa 1930s-circa 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Diploma, 1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters to Keck, 1920-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Speeches, circa 1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lists of Artwork, Prices, and Sales, circa 1920s-circa 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lists of Artwork, Bound Volume, circa 1920s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lists of Artwork, "Work Done", 1931-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lists of Artwork, "Work Done," Binder, 1931-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Printed Material, Clippings and Statements on Post Office Relief, 1933-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Printed Material, "Presidents North Carolina Gave the Nation", 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Photographic Material, circa 1905-circa 1948; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 8.3 Linear feet Boxes 1-22
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged as two subseries.
  2.1: Photographs, circa 1905-circa 1948 (0.3 linear feet; Boxes 1-2)
  2.2: Glass Plate Negatives, circa 1920s-circa 1940s (8 linear feet; Boxes 12-22)
  The bulk of this series has been digitized. Photographs that are copy prints of glass plate negatives have not been digitized.
  - Photographs, circa 1905-circa 1948; 2.1; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
    Photographs of Keck include two with his wife, Anne, at a circa 1920 Beaux Arts Ball at the Astor Hotel in New York City, and one photo of him with his youngest son, John. There are also portraits of Keck and photos of him in his studio, including one from circa 1905 at the American Academy in Rome with his sculpture "The Awakening of Egypt." There are copy prints of family members, including Anne Keck, unidentified individuals, including two men sitting for portraits, and three group photographs of Keck, Adolph Weinman, Milton Horn, and others. Some of the copy prints have been printed from the glass plate negatives in Series 2.2. Also found are photos of the unveiling of Keck's monument to Presidents Jackson, Polk, and Johnson in Raleigh, North Carolina, including photos showing President Harry S. Truman and Margaret Truman, state and government officials James McCord, Willis Smith, R. Gregg Cherry, Clyde R. Hoey, and William B. Umstead, and the lunch following the unveiling at the Governor's Mansion in Raleigh, in October 1948.
    - Keck and Others, 1920s-1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Keck in Studio, circa 1905-1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Keck in Studio, circa 1905-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Studio, circa 1910; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Family, circa 1905-circa 1920s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Men Sitting for Portraits, circa 1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Events Celebrating Unveiling Of Keck Monument in Raleigh, NC, 1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Events Celebrating Unveiling Of Keck Monument in Raleigh, NC, 1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Works of Art, circa 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Works of Art, circa 1920s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Works of Art, In Studio, 1933; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Works of Art, In Studio, 1933; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Works of Art, Models for Edison Memorial, Eagle Rock, NJ, circa 1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Works of Art, Negatives, circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Glass Plate Negatives, circa 1920s-circa 1940s; 2.2; Archival Resource Key; 8 Linear feet Boxes 12-22
    1003 glass plate negatives are primarily of artwork by Keck including busts, carvings, reliefs, plaques, medallions, statues, pillars, and paintings, photographed both in the studio and on location. The last box in the series contains a few images of people, including Anne Keck, and of Keck's studio, some of which appear to have copy prints in series 2.1. Photographs.
    Approximately one half of the images are numbered according to a system that is referenced in a list of negatives, numbers 400-533, which appears to record the works of art in rough chronological order, ending around 1931. The unnumbered negatives are from circa 1927- to the early 1940s. The original order of the negatives has been maintained.
    - List of Negatives #400-533, circa 1924-circa 1933; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Numbers 1-38, circa 1920s-circa 1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
    - Numbers 39-87, circa 1920s-circa 1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 4)
    - Numbers 88-138, circa 1920s-circa 1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 5)
    - Numbers 139-189, circa 1920s-circa 1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 6)
    - Numbers 190-237, circa 1920s-circa 1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 7)
    - Numbers 238-407, circa 1920s-circa 1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 8)
    - Numbers 408-457, circa 1920s-circa 1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 9)
    - Numbers 458-503B, circa 1920s-circa 1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 10)
    - Numbers 504C-533 and Unnumbered, circa 1920s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 11)
    - Unnumbered, circa 1920s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 12)
    - Unnumbered, circa 1920s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 13)
    - Unnumbered, circa 1920s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 14)
    - Unnumbered, circa 1920s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 15)
    - Unnumbered, circa 1920s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 16)
    - Unnumbered, circa 1920s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 17)
    - Unnumbered, circa 1920s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 18)
    - Unnumbered, circa 1920s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 19)
    - Unnumbered, circa 1920s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 20)
    - Unnumbered, circa 1920s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 21)
    - Unnumbered, circa 1920s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 22)